welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where equal hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
another the same when you're talking
check-ins okay I feel a primordial
calmness right now and it feels pretty
good
welcome to the stoah my name is Peter
Lindbergh on the Stewart of the stoah
and the stoah is a place for us to
cohere and dialogue about what matters
most at the nice edge of this moment and
today is gonna be awesome today is gonna
put me at the edge of my thinking and I
will hand it over to our emcee of the
evening soon Nicolas Lee mocker and
Nicolas is sort of like he's become like
the talent scout of the stoy he's
finding all these like cool people is
hapy gotta do this person we gotta talk
to this person and then he introduced me
to Carl maybe two weeks ago and I'm like
who the fuck is this guy his guy's
awesome and then when we had a zoom chat
I was like okay yeah confirmed
really stoked about this session so I'm
gonna hand it over to Nicolas now and
he's gonna tell us how the sessions
gonna work and then we're going to hear
from the speaker today so floors yours
my friend awesome thank you so hey
everybody I'm Nick I'll be hosting
today's stoah session and yeah it's
gonna work the same way that they always
work you guys can ask your questions in
the chat box if you want me to read them
out just indicate that it's gonna be
recorded so just keep that in mind and
yeah Carl we have a really really
special guest that I came across at the
awaken future summit a few weeks ago and
that when he presented I was absolutely
mind-blowing and I'm really happy that
he can now present his work here with
with the stoah folks so yeah to
introduce Carl
I'll just take what's on the website
that's always the my best bet so Carl is
director of the learning Technology
Research Center and
simple research fellow at Robbins burn
University he has 16 years experience
conducting R&D into the application of
hybrid technologies for perceptual and
cognitive transformation he's also the
founder of the cyber Delic Society so
yeah really really exciting stuff and
yeah let's just hear it from Carl Carl
thanks so much Luke and pizza so yeah
I'm gonna break the talk down into into
six parts and we'll go through them
pretty rapidly so I'm going to talk
about the origins of the term double
consciousness and the and some
definitions of it then I'm going to talk
about the background into why I'm
actually interested in this area and why
it's relevant research for today and
then we're going to go into some
examples and application areas then
we're going to counter those application
areas with some counter arguments and
then we're going to have some
quantifiable benefits and some
conclusions so in terms of a lot of what
I'm going to talk about today I've just
published a paper at the British
Computer Society and the paper is called
living in parallel adventures in double
consciousness and pluralism so in terms
of the origins of the term we have de
bois in 1897 using double consciousness
to describe the internal conflict
experienced by subordinated groups in an
oppressive society very apt for these
moments African Americans can experience
a double consciousness from being an
American and African American at the
same time Aldous Huxley also alluded to
double consciousness in 1962 when he
states that we have to be us oneself and
completely something else at the same
time which is the whole secret of life
and the importance of taking regular
holidays from the self I'm particularly
interested in Roy ascots take on double
consciousness in 1999 stated double
consciousness gives access in parallel
to two distinctly different fields of
experience the shamanic trance in which
the Shaymin is both in the everyday
world and at the same time navigating
outermost limits of other worlds I which
is arguably now mirrored by our ability
to move through the infinities
cyberspace whilst within the structures
of the material world he goes on
immersion in such no etics simulation
may induce real changes of consciousness
and eventually real transformations of
the self this techno shamanism may lead
to an evolution of cognition where the
subject object relationship is dissolved
and reality begins to be actively
constructed rather than passively
observed and ontological design is the
forefront here so one of the things that
made me very interested in these forms
of escape is the hikikomori in Japan and
there's half a million of them that have
logged out society I want to Winston
Churchill fellowship to go to Japan in
2014 and obviously very difficult to
study those those guys because they're
all locked away already but they're
basically saying it's too hard societies
too hard I'm not going to take part
anymore so how do we how do we try and
stop that and if we think about virtual
reality creating these escape routes
ready player one scenarios where people
just use the reality that they're in the
physical reality is a base layer for
jumping into the virtual where you can
be whoever you want to be you can you
know limited by sex by how you look by
all the usual physical restraints but
one of the really interesting areas I
think of double consciousness now is the
the death shadow that we're all facing
Zack Bush a brilliant did a brilliant
podcast recently where he's talking
about the fact that he's working with
the dying and he's working with people
that he's bringing back from the death
state and to quote him let me tell you
about what my experience has been in
those last moments with patients who are
dying we'd have the belief in our
subconscious I think because of movies
and TV shows we watch of a big divorce
in the death process which has become
sterilized and allowed death to be
defined as an endpoint as a contraction
or a disappearance rather than what I've
actually seen it to be which is a
massive expansion of consciousness and
awareness and he talks about people
coming
back bringing people back from the dead
and they all asked why did you bring me
back as if we're kind of like you know
in a prison in this reality in the
physical realms and that always strikes
me as interesting from the transhumanist
so you want to prolong life indefinitely
maybe this isn't maybe this is the
rehearsal for something else a lot of my
work is looking at the ancient mystery
schools and that's why I'm so interested
in the stoah because of you know the all
the Greek philosophers went into those
mystery schools into the inner mysteries
eight hundred years they ran for and we
don't know what exactly went on in there
because initiates were sentenced to
death if they spoke about what what
happened to them in those three days but
we know almost certainly that there was
a psychedelic involved we know that
there was a rebirth and a death and a
rebirth process much like the Masons go
through today and we and we know that
there was sensory deprivation etc so
what's interesting is that you enter
this liminal space and then you come
back changed I also have my own
experience you'll experience of a life
review where I stopped living going
forwards and my entire life was shown to
me in Reverse so I lived in these
episodic states going backwards so I was
in my normal state of consciousness but
also in my in my consciousness in in
those episodic States and I was able to
quite realize quite quickly that I was
able to leave my body in that state in
that in that double consciousness and
enter a triple consciousness where I
could enter anything else so I went and
the first thing I tried was going into a
table and experiencing what it was like
to be would does in the experience of
being wood in myself and in myself a
trip of consciousness and then long
story showing
went back two years I was going out with
a girl in Berlin she got pregnant by
mistake and in the time sheet she founds
me up in I'm in London shoots and
bonuses I'm I'm putting the abortions on
Tuesday slams the phone down I go over
to Berlin she has the abortion she takes
a pill so it's very newly pregnant and
I'm aware in my in my life of you that I
can go into her body so I go into her
body and I don't and I experience what
it's like to be pregnant I also
experience all the anxiety etc cetera
but then I'm able to like choose to
into the womb and experience the
abortion at a cellular level so I mean a
quadruple consciousness in a parallel
consciousness and for me this has really
changed my perception of what
consciousness is and this idea of
consciousness and literacy is what I'm
talking about here so if we think about
paradox management that's also something
that can have that double consciousness
can help holding two positions at the
same time I mean if we think about a
tree a dead tree in the forest it's also
an ecosystem of new life so what what is
that that is the paradox of this this
state that we're in and a great point
from rebel wisdom our festival recently
David fuller mentioned that we're in a
self terminating system but we are also
in the best time to be alive so how can
both things be true and how can we hold
those two perspectives without
collapsing one into the other
so yeah we're in a deeply fragile
situation right now but what I'm trying
to come up with is solutions
and whether we can gain something from
this parallel living and if we think so
moving on to some examples and
application areas we think about optical
illusions one of the key attributes or
functions of double consciousness as
I've mentioned is this idea of the
ability to expand your perceptual field
to give access at one at the same time
to two distinctly theater two distinctly
different fields of experience my
colleague Kevin Davidson in the paper I
mentioned he talked about optical
illusions with optical illusions there's
a moment of pleasure when the second
perspective comes into focus it's almost
like a little flash of enlightenment as
our awareness broadens like suddenly
seeing out of a part of our eyes which
we didn't have access to before
experiences such as these are like
medicine for our consciousness
broadening our perceptive bandwidth and
leaving us with an awareness that we are
agents in constructing our reality so
that's absolutely central to the whole
thesis so I'll talk a little bit about
some examples a robot and a paper so
living in virtual reality
we're running a protocol seeing-eye with
mark for rid where he's gonna live
through somebody else for a month we've
already launched it I was electrónica in
Austria where he lived through 14
different people in in 14 days and so he
was a so he's wearing virtual reality
but he's not looking into a game
environment he's looking into somebody
else's eyes so somebody else has been
wearing a camera recording their day and
and so he's looking through their day
and basically not accessing his own his
own hearing or his own sight and the
reason why he originally chose 28 days
is because that's how long it takes to
form habits and what he wants to try and
do is dissolve his own identity and
adopt somebody else's to see if this
idea of we all know that the self is a
construction and narrative construction
so he's testing that and seeing how much
we can dissolve it and you know you've
also got loads of examples now in
virtual reality there's one that's quite
controversial which is helping pregnant
women with childbirth so that they're
kind of not you know that is this isn't
during the birth this is build up to the
birth during all the pain that they go
through and there's loads of examples
where people are like having burned
Burns victim soldiers that have been
burned that they've put on a VR headset
so that they're distracted away from the
physical and can be taken into the to
the other and friends of mine that are
in chronic pain you know we're looking
at solutions where they don't focus on
their pain they focus on a visualization
of their pain that we placed between
them and their pain and they try and
change that that visualization which is
an accurate rendition of the pain in
order to change the pain so it's
creating these models that show you that
reality is a construction so the second
example is this idea of dream hacking
and you know we now know that people
lucid dream reliably lucid dream but the
average person gets one lucid dream if
they're lucky I had one lucid dream so
far and I was just there with a
calculator consciously choosing the
numbers and it was like completely
retarded and I hope I get to do another
one but
knowledge ease enabling us now we know
the transcranial stimulation may help
put us applied whilst you're in a REM
state may actually produce a lucid dream
if you combine that with some nootropics
like galantamine then you you're getting
closer to a reliable lucid dream state
and I'm really interested in the fact
that you know you're you're in two
places at the same time because you are
consciously choosing to change the dream
and you know I'll talk a little bit
about why that may be problematic but I
think that that we know that people that
reliably do dream yoga that they're
practicing say Taichi in a dream state
and they're reporting that it's four
times more effective in terms of their
Tai Chi practice because they're
applying the context as well as doing
the activity they have to apply gravity
for instance quite often you start at
least dreaming your flow off the floor
because you haven't applied that that
parameter and I'm also interested in
hypnagogia and hypnopompic because again
when you're in this so to explain what
those are this is when you're like
you're falling asleep and you enter this
liminal space where you may get great
ideation or just when you're waking up I
tend to write tons when I'm sort of half
asleep waking out of a dream because I'm
in between those worlds in this liminal
space and Edison famously had a
technology where I'll take me rather
where he would hold ball-bearings
over a pan and as he was falling asleep
he would drop the ball bearings and then
that would wake him up and he would
write down the ideas that he would
access and those in my space so the
third example is this one of DMT
extended technology so I've been lucky
enough to be part of the Imperial
studies where they're injecting me with
pure DMT and scanning my brain and fMRI
scanner um I don't recommend it although
it was the most profound one of most
profound experiences of my life I'm not
gonna go into that that's in other talks
but the DMT extended experiences when
you can be kept on a drip and and fed
DMT and
in that realm you know maybe for 40
minutes then for 4 hours then for you
know 4 days so you know the idea from
Gallimore is that he's looking at using
the third dimension to to launch into
hyperspace permanently where your body
is kept in a you know in a pod and waste
management is taken care of all of your
bodily needs etc so you're you know
you're fed food etc the reason why I'm
interested in it even though I think
it's quite problematic and the double
question is point of view is that
whenever I take DMT I see this language
at the core of my vision which is
consistent and it's you know it's
ancient and modern at the same time if
these hieroglyphs and if I'm live I'm in
a DMT extended-stay I could potentially
sit there and draw it and bring back
something from this this dream state a
lot of you know all of us struggle tips
further to remember our dreams as soon
as I need them we in the morning that's
it as soon as that process is happening
my dream is rapidly disappearing so I'd
love to bring things back from dream
states and and there's arguments
especially out for stimulants research
that DMT in terms of brain signature is
very similar to a dreaming state and
then another example would be so just to
finish on that so a DMT extended
experience or a DMT experience even you
know if your body is kept in a pod
you're not really aware of the body you
know so you're not really in a double
cream since you're just in hyperspace
and a more authentic example of double
consciousness you could argue is
something that I learned from a
brilliant podcast by Lauren fields with
Andy lecture where he's talking about
the difference between cordyceps and the
general synergistic value of mushrooms
magic mushrooms so cordyceps is when an
ant is infected by this mushroom
cordyceps and the ant carries on as
normal doesn't really know it's been
infected and it's literally the mushroom
is infected it's muscles it's around its
brain and when when the mushroom decides
it wants to reproduce
it triggers the the aunt into this
remote controlled state where it climbs
to the tallest tree it can find it
chomps down on the on the on this
specifically for a specific angle and
and it basically then needs to you know
the the the the body of the ad is
dissolved and then mushrooms come out of
the body of the an and spores come out
of the mushroom spreading to all the
ants beneath so you know again not
really a double consciousness even
though you could argue that yeah the
mushroom are cohabiting the same space
at a certain time but it's more of a
zombification from the ant whereas if
you think about the psilocybin
containing mushrooms we know that there
are two hundred-plus mushrooms we found
that out we found out how to you know
prepare those mushrooms to take
ourselves so we're spreading the
mushrooms across the world we are in the
service of the mushroom but in in in
return the mushroom we as we ingest it
is allowing our consciousness to see the
world in a more mushroomy way and i
think that is a much more likely you
know version of double consciousness
where both parts of the equation are
being nourished at the same time so you
know this idea of you know the human and
the nonhuman i think if we're gonna
really learn we need to learn from
something more intelligent than us and
you could argue that is the mycelium the
mushroom has survived five mass
extinctions and we're causing the sixth
so the fact that the mushroom is you
know allowing us to rather the mushroom
shares when it when it's in abundance so
you know we can learn from that if we
don't then we're not gonna survive so
looking at that sort of thing but also
you know about hacking which is when you
actually hack in the censorial system of
another creature brilliant examples from
marshmallow laser please great vote of
the are outfit where you're able to to
experience
different species through VR but a
brilliant example from the paper is the
the one from Steven Harding where in his
short film encountering another being he
talks about the monk jack and and
experiencing the monk Jack's
consciousness I could immediately
understand the wholeness of the monk
jack and how they relate to the entire
wood and it went further than that I
could also get a sense of the ecology of
the whole forest it suddenly came into
focus through the being of the monk Jack
the whole came into my perception and
then if I was very lucky I that spread
that wholeness would spread and spread
out and I'd get a sense of the ecology
of the entire earth so you know what's
fascinating about that is his his
interaction enables him to multiply and
amplify the experience in order to to
apply it to the entire environment so
moving from content engineering to
context engineering and then the the
final sort of example from from my own
expect experience is one of journaling
and from me I've written a diary 230
years I've written it from three
different levels so I write content
white done context how I felt and
concepts White's thoughts it's five
minutes a day it's incredibly easy to do
if you just get into the habit of doing
it and the benefits are marvelous
because you're you know you're forced to
live you can't keep getting the Newton
you can't get Saint you can't write same
material down every day so you have to
get a new material every day you know
you can read a relationship and an
afternoon say that you know been in a
relationship for a years on 50 60 pages
you can read all that in an afternoon
you get a map and get a bird's-eye view
of the whole relationship and then what
I do is I take cross sections through
that that that database and I'm seeing
my life you know 30 different means so
look at this day last year perform year
before the year before me it before and
I creates a plurality I'm able to you
know get those 30 means communicating
again and I'm also able to understand
what it is useful to do in retrospect
because I've kept this this ability to
jump out of the the point of view and go
into the field of view so I'm literally
creating this double-consciousness of
around my own life and that ability to
see in the overview getting you
effect is amazing and a brilliant point
raised again in the rebel wisdom
festivals
one nor a base and mentioned which is
where can you go to find what the
question was where can you go to find
sources of wisdom and her answer was I
get wisdom from everywhere and and
therefore it's like for me you know it's
like this idea wisdom is gained by
taking a higher-order perspective on
your own perspective so it's I'm mining
my own life to create my own wisdom this
tool allows me to relive past
experiences but from an alternate
alternate perspective from the person I
am now to go back to those decisions to
try and learn why I made those decisions
granting me a greater in-depth
understanding where I become wiser but
only if I've been honest with myself and
I'm still honest with myself so
counter-arguments Huxley as my colleague
liane Crane mentioned that you know he
in his doors of perception he argues you
know don't make the best of all worlds
but in his final years he spent time
warning people about the dangers of
escaping into a nirvana apart from the
world if we think about the living in VR
example you know living inside somebody
else can again be aligned with escapism
and you know the whole VR is pain relief
thing great when it's applied to the to
the soldiers they're having their burns
replaced but their dressings replaced
but not so great if you're trying to
maintain a natural experience of birth
and diem TX the counter-argument there
is you know judge Chuck Charles Locker
states there is a danger that the
psychedelic state is being over
romanticized DMT extended could be
argued to be a new form of biochemical
VR where we are getting stuck into
another game of Thrones that is not on
the screen but inside our own minds we
have to rise above everything being
reduced to entertainment otherwise we
look upon junkies of altered states that
don't go anywhere so the counter to that
counter is the idea that if we are
plugging in
an orthogonal reality rather than a
dream state then we're actually
exploring other realms we'll come back
to that and then the the final one the
dream hacking one you know do we really
want to spend our times you know in in
lucid dream states doing more work you
know I'm actually like worried that if I
do have reliable dream state I will just
read all the papers I don't get time to
read in normal life so I'll scan them
before bed and then I'll read them in my
dream state so everything becomes work
and also you know some of my friends
that are actually dreaming a.length they
spend all their days writing those
dreams down so they're not really in a
nested ecology they're just in this
escapist world so moving on to the
benefits quantifiable quantifiable
benefits I think the the conscious state
shifting if we if we describe state
shifting is recognition of what state
you're in and the ability to observe
verse blend with States or the ability
to surrender to challenging States and
the ability to also shift States at will
so moving from the thinker to the
observer of the thing goes and fantastic
and moving the observer around
Heather Hargreaves doing some amazing
work in stage shifting and if you think
about this idea of perceptual
flexibility through perspective shifting
going back to neuro Bateson's argument
about getting wisdom from everywhere and
there's one of the audience members said
so what is the feeling of that what is
the mechanism by which you can tune into
the relationships between all of the
different places where you might get
wisdom from so much of the time it's
about noticing the pull of one thing or
another to one story or narrative or to
one way of thinking or another and
resisting the pull and staying in that
liminal space in between the two poles
and seeing how long you can hold that
space and noticing what happens in that
bridge that you have built so again
going back to the hypnopompic magog
exteme you're in between worlds and this
also relates to java vacu stuff around
relevance realization and salience
Landscaping I won't have time to go into
so other forms of perceptual flexibility
like I mentioned this idea of holding
paradox
the ability to be inside a lucid dream
practicing tai chi or Qigong or whatever
it is you want to practice cognitive
diversity is another benefit and
brilliant work by Mel Slater where he's
putting people in VR into into a
drummer's body for instance so they can
practice drama so they're in a famous or
drummers body and they're drumming and
they're drumming improves because
they're inside the body of a famous
drummer so it's this all of this sort of
stuff and these does brilliant work
around race and prisoners and all the
rest of it and I think that the sixth
benefit is this idea of reimagining the
imagination or encouraging the use of
imagination and a lot of what I'm
talking about
is about the imagination of course and
Kevin Davidson against States I think
this is fundamental to child development
we talk about the Waldorf schools as
schooling the imagination it's ever more
important when children are having a lot
of their imagination done for them and
they're and they have less opportunity
to be bored with nothing to do ie no
sensory input coming at them watching
Disney films is like toxic white sugar
for the imagination you've planted a
seed for something about what the
driving edge of VR can teach you know
how we prepare children for the future
so it's all for me about not replacing
imagination with computer animation not
being prescriptive creating worlds that
are declarative that our maps that you
can walk around without being told where
to go so to conclude obviously the
problem with double consciousness is
that it implies a polarity it implies
Jew and dualism and consciousness itself
is obviously infinite to us although we
may just spend all of our times in the
reception room of our minds rather than
in the infinity of our potential and
which is what I'm hoping to open and
unlock this this human potential rather
than the human downgrading that what
we're doing with current technologies
with these tiny little screens and small
real estate
so different belts demonstrate there are
many manifestations of consciousness
there are as many manifestations of
consciousness as there are beings all
coexisting in the universe and the
multiverse
so pluralism represents multiple ways of
knowing so you know moving from double
consciousness to pluralism pluralism is
about multiple ways of knowing or
multiple ontology --zz unity in
diversity and you know I think that a
lot of what we're seeing is this idea of
dealing with dealing with other nests
holding on to with this integral view
holding on to multiplicity hybridity the
I we it model and brilliant quote from
Eric Davis now there is something about
the interpersonal there is something
about the other one of the problems with
the non dual vision of unity is that it
dissolves the radical claim of the other
the outside and the beyond as we become
posthuman and and we wake up to the fact
that we are absolutely embedded in these
non-human forces systems and
relationships instead of emphasizing
unity we should be focusing on pluralism
the actual nature of reality is multiple
and Grant Morrison I think you will be a
future guest on the stoah he talks about
this idea of the ecology of selves are
we going to stick to these personalities
these bounded territorial things or are
we going to expand ourselves into
something bigger
the first thing you have to change is
yourself this change this can be
achieved through understanding your dark
side for instance let us become Plex
creatures so we're able to take on new
personality traits and able to extend
our boundaries into what was previously
the enemy enemy territory and yeah this
is a good an essential practice to
demonstrate to ourselves that we are
co-creating our reality and if you think
about an ecology of practices wisdom is
found by a cultivating an ecology of
practices whether it's mindful inquiry
biological inquiry mimetic inquiry and
again
not Norah Bates and brilliant session on
warm data real wisdom she talked about
triple context ting asking the same
questions through three context at the
same time again living in parallel I'm a
lot of what I've talked about just to
finish is this is language I'm talking
about metaphors I'm talking about living
in two places at the same time I'm
talking about multiple scales so I need
to look now what is how much of
languages is impacting on my thinking
but also I want to build a typology a
taxonomy of these different types of
double consciousness and moving on to
the pluralist stuff but what I hope I've
shown you is that it's not about
building new realms of Augmented escape
escapism but building new forms of
consciousness and literacy and if we can
increase plurality we can increase
tolerance please feel free to message me
if you on the paper thank you I feel
very excited very very alive after
hearing that because there's so many
thoughts though many ideas that just
come rushing in and that's it's it's
fascinating work that you're doing so
what I the first thing I wanted to to
say is that
I really enjoyed that you didn't use
slides this time around because the last
time I listened to you you did use
slides and there's a lot of insane
beautiful content that you use there so
for all the people listening on YouTube
there's quite a few presentations where
call presents some of these ideas using
some some of the slides that emphasize
the content so I highly recommend
checking that out and so there are quite
a few cool questions in the in the chat
box but before we go there I had a
question but I'm thinking of how to
rephrase it after this this presentation
one thing I've been thinking a lot about
is I think it comes from Alexander bard
where he says something like the
machines are going to be the best at
being the machines right they're gonna
be absolutely great AI all that so we as
humans should be the best humans that we
can be right so that we can later
develop some sort of symbiotic
intelligence between these two and then
he uses logos to talk about the machine
and pathos to talk about the human and
then to find a shared Methos between
those two and so I guess a question in
that regard would be that it seems like
you're expanding what it means to be
human in some ways and and what we're
able to do as humans so you call it
hyper humanism so maybe if you could
riff a bit on hyper humanism and and
perhaps also share what your thoughts
are on where this narrative will come
from right I mean we can have these
practices that will inform the things
that we do but you don't don't you sense
that we need us some sort of narrative
to inform our actions in the future yeah
so the hyper humanist stuff is a counter
to a transhumanist agenda so I did a
keynote with Ray Kurzweil last year in
Melbourne innovation and we were talking
we were framing around intelligence 2.0
like what where where do we go with this
stuff and we look at the transhumanist
there they're trying to prolong life
potentially indefinitely although Ray
was unwell at the time and started to
sort of talk about maybe for a long life
a certain quality of life rather than
indefinite extension and and also
they're very much dependent on
technology and what I'm trying to do
with my work is find those those
opportunities where we can use a
technology to kick-start an ability that
we may already have in our analog world
in our analog world is being rocked
we're being robbed of our analog
abilities because of poorly designed
technologies and you know I'm always
quoting this example from from cyborg
myths because I work with them on on
there and they're news central north
sense which is about to updated and so
all it is is a little chip that you wear
and their tagline is transhumanist one
they say we don't want to we don't want
to wear technology we want to become it
and and I I think that's problematic
primarily because you know we may have
already had the north sense and lost it
because of the use of technology and I
think technology atrophies muscles that
we actually have anyway an example is
one of my friends you know it doesn't
use the internet until he absolutely
needs to because it's a giant brain and
he wants to actually find things out for
himself so of course that can't be often
often the case but to go back to cyborgs
nest I think the the general idea is
that yeah it vibrates every time you
face north after a few weeks you've got
that as a new sense you know it's like
[Music]
but also this there's an example from a
different device called feel space which
is where you wear a belt
it's got vibration motors in it it
vibrates every time you face north in
exactly the same way but the difference
is is that you take that off with this
with a cyborg mist version you leave it
on and it's permanently attached to you
the field space belt you take off after
six to eight weeks and you still have
that new sense so I'm really interested
in like you know imagine stabilizers on
your bike you remove the stabilizers and
you have the new skin
cycling so that's how I see technology
and that's human isms I'm unlocking your
innate human abilities or human
potential but you didn't know you have
and maybe just using technology catalyst
to get there I can you remind me the
second part of the question it's more
about the narrative about how we should
be using this so how do we inform that I
guess the ethos like what is the I mean
it sounds amazing all the things that
you're doing and it's like very
experimental in some ways right but is
that what is there any sense of ethics
that you rely on I guess in a bit in
some sense um well I think that's why
I'm so fascinated by creating frameworks
of you surround these things and I think
a lot of the time it's it's a literacy
thing I mean Quitely working on a death
literacy project because I think we're
all in the death shadow at the moment
and and I think it's you know it's all
around education like the same with
psychedelics you know that this there's
certain frameworks of uses around set
and setting and I'm understanding that
you know certain setting it's just as
important as the actual substance same
with technology the hype humanists
approach I think that people aren't
aware of it and they're losing their you
know we give we give up so much agency
to the technologies and that we we lose
the fact that we are the ultimate
technology and that's that's it for me
it's it's all of all about you know how
do we get there with our own their own
stuff and how do we how do we educate
ourselves I think that a lot of the
technologies are being co-opted the
agendas of the of the corporations are
not they're not looking out for us so I
think it's about DIY approaches it's
about getting good news stories out
there around technology and Tristan
Harris the sense of humane technology is
doing a fantastic job very succinctly
puts into a single two page PDF what
what is why how they're how they're
basically achieving this human
downgrading and what we can do about it
awesome well I mean there's so many
questions that would want to follow up
with but there's uh maybe gray had a
really nice question yeah I'm good
thanks Nick
my question was I I hear this tension in
these kind of like technological realms
between the opportunities we have to
explore and the temptations we may have
to escape I'm wondering if you could
speak a little bit on how we can like
tell in our bodies the difference
between those two impulses in ourselves
so that we can try to develop a
sensitivity and make better decisions
yeah it's a good one isn't it I think I
think you're right because we're so I
mean again my friend Jackie Lucas
talking about young people how they're
very much used to this low-level
stimulation all the time so they're kind
of like they're not getting bored
they're not feeling into the fact that
these technologies are uh you know just
they're not they're not your friend a
lot of the time and it's about
disengaging a lot of the time I mean
there's a brilliant example where my
friend Hannah and a close was talking
about this is article about Buddhism and
the oculus rift and how how the oculus
will will transform Buddhism and how
organisms doesn't need to be augmented
it's already you know something that's
been practiced for millennia and you
know but you know you could argue that
that same thing that the Buddhists you
know may have may have said the same
thing about Buddhism to the Buddha I
mean it's like I think that it's about
having cognitive sovereignty you know
you you need to this to be able to
disengage to spend time away from the
gadgets to to to realize that you know
your ability to explore your
consciousness is your birthright and the
information over
load disability to dis disengage and
turn down the volume of the the thinker
the brain the constant brain chatter
like you know it's always like your
lavish you're rubbish rubbish so it's
it's it's it's having holidays from the
self but having them in in it as
healthier way as you can not just going
into the into the escapist realms which
is so prevalent and I think again it's
literacy around escapism
but we need to generate thank you for
the question and then maybe a good
follow up question would be Peter Peters
question Thank You Nick it might have
already been asked eldest hour answered
I should say but I'll ask it again in
the asking the frame that I worded in
okay so once you have access to the
psychology of states in the survey if
you have the capacity for ontological
diversity how do you determine what
state to access like how do you kind of
like navigate them and it's like what 2
maybes question if we're not gonna be
consumers of cautiousness know what are
we going to be like explorers there's or
something more to be than just an
explorer yeah I mean it's practice it's
absolutely practice and it comes back to
the state shifting thing you know if
you're you know if you're if you're
having these feedback loops that
neurofeedback creates this ability to
you know much like the quantified self
idea that you're you're accessing these
these these realms of the inner the
inner machinery and I think it's a
brilliant question Thea because it's so
it's so
alien to us that we have all this these
inner realms and and yeah I think it's
it's it's practice it's ultimately
literacy it's about knowing that you can
do these things I mean I've just signed
up for the thinker the finders course
which is thousand different types of
meditation and you know it's pick a mix
kind of 17 week course and Josh fields
actually recommended it to me because
one of my big projects is this idea of
how do we do
I mean uh what I've learnt from the
psychedelic society with Jose is that
it's very niche you know trying to
create altered states with technology
it's it's quite a niche area but what
isn't niche is the fact that we have a
thousand different types of meditation
we have a thousand different types of
breathing we have a thousand different
types of dance so how can we put all of
those things how can we create stacks as
in like Jamie will talks a lot about
these idea we've got the breath work
we've got the meditation we've got all
these things that are already there and
it's around practicing like different
breathing techniques to see what what
ontological stake it results in and
obviously we have cultural differences
and gender differences and everything
else so it's citizen science actually
approach that we need to create it's you
know it's this it's this ability to
start with some meditation do some
breath work go into VR experience come
out of the view experience maybe take a
microdose do some more breath work you
know it's endless
it's endless and that's why frameworks
are so important if you have a five
question regarding the framework to like
so I'm reminded the my cultural analysis
where there's like an ecology of
memeplex is out there in the noosphere
and the idea is once you have an
intimacy with them not only a
propositional level but on a felt sense
level you can get into right
relationship from them and then get this
signal get the truth without getting
triggered or hijacked by their sort of
echoic machinations and I'm seeing some
sort of a similar project where there's
an ecology of different ontological
states and then one of the first moves
is just to be an explorer there so you
can get into right relationship with it
and then you can know what to turn on
when you need to turn it on is that sort
of the right read yeah absolutely and I
think that it's that it's that holistic
approach way and that's why I love all
the rebel wisdom stuff and in the sense
making in the meaning crisis because
it's all about feeling we've been
thinking ourselves to death and I think
that you combining your intuition with
your comment you know your cognition is
absolutely what we need to be doing the
we were just were just carrying our
heads around and in our bodies and not
really doing the bodywork and I think as
soon as you're sitting down and you're
staring in front of a screen your your
whole creative apparatus is switched off
you need to be in movement and that's
what I'm really interested in the mixed
reality technologies where we can do
away with this constant sitting and
actually be in the world still and
actually you know have our our movement
to actually create these these holistic
creative creative ways of being mmm
thank you
and I just follow what would be
Brandon's question yeah thanks thanks
cows have been fascinating my question
is just what is the relationship between
double consciousness and empathic past
do you think there's a lot of overlap
for me at least let's say that I can
implement empathic capacity being an
empath yeah absolutely and I think that
you know empathise have I mean people
talked about virtual reality as an
empathy engine in the early days and I
think that's been pretty discredited now
and for me it's it's about compassion a
lot of there's a book coming the author
against empathy and because you know a
lot of the time if you're empathizing
with somebody without the compassion
it's kind of it can be destabilizing and
you can actually be in the same state
and not able to help them if you're if
you're you know without the compassion
so for me absolutely you know if we were
in it with prisoners of our own selves
and I think anything that enables us to
have the felt experience of another you
know I'm super interested in you know
all the different techniques around
since making others but also
disassociative xand and the ability to
dissolve the self and actually enter
enter
you know possession you know being
possessed is such a fascinating realm
and
yeah I think it's a fantastic question
and I'd love to have a follow-up I'm
liking this idea I'm just curious like
those who claim to be empaths are they
do you feel that they are experiencing
some double consciousness state or is
there something different happening here
yeah I mean it's I'm always trying to
counter the whole double consciousness
thing as well as promoter ID I think and
Camille's Oster brilliant question
around DMT and my DMT experiences I
think the most profound thing that the
empties taught me is the absolutely
telepathy is real and you know and you
know when I was having my brain scanned
in the scanner and left memorize I was
it was very incredible because there the
amount of entities that turned up on
mass all different varieties all saying
to me what the hell's happening to you
you know because obviously I'm in a
scanner and the setting setting was
completely transformed and that the the
the benevolence of these creatures all
like just like wanting to help and on
you know sort of telepathically sort of
showing me visually that I'm immortal
but currently in a human body
and basically saying don't die don't
know whatever you do and I spent the
entire like 40 minutes in that scanner
trying to calm them down which was a
very interesting Nick you know double
consciousness and you know I really you
know III Telep telepathy is real
depending on you know your your your the
way you're viewing things and and what
you're viewing through and you know
totally agree awesome and then rain you
have two questions so I like both of
them so whichever one feels more alive
to you I guess thanks um this is
fascinating
thank you so much for being here my
question is about these this the
plurality consciousness maybe double
consciousness I don't know quite the
distinctions but the plurality
consciousness do you see that from an
integral perspective as a higher stage
or a state or some combination yeah
absolutely I think that's where where
we're headed if we're lucky to to live
long enough and you know I again I've
had these transformative experiences
where I've gone into a realm or a
dimension where I which I would classed
as a fifth dimensional realm where I'm
I'm I'm aware of everyone's thoughts
there's and there's no longer any
privacy it's you know everything and
everyone knows everything about you it's
kind of it's just done you know it so it
also you know had experiences of you
know I never had one reading in my life
but the guy was like you know when you
when you've completed your mission on
earth you get all of your lives back you
you know much like I'm doing with my
diary I have this ability to unlock 30
different knees because I'm daily going
through these cross sections and turning
my life itself into architecture these
parallel worlds where I'm I'm creating
that muscle I'm creating that
pluralistic way of seeing where I'm I'm
not just in the in the point of view
everyone goes on about and it's all
about being in the moment I would argue
absolutely but also be all of those
selves at the same time and and you know
and it doesn't take much to actually
access that plurality it's just a
practice it's something that you need to
build up and oh yeah for me that I
focused on the double constants but I
want to write a whole paper on what you
just asked for maybe I can still ask a
quick question so
like what came up is okay so these are
not are they sometimes lasting effects
or how long do they last because it
isn't it is a practice and you're like
training a muscle and the stronger than
muscle I guess they're the longer the
effects last but sometimes I guess
depending on
yeah whichever of the many experiences
you've you've participated in are there
some that had a longer lasting effect
than others yeah I mean I had now a body
experience 27 and that for me was the
beginning of all of this journey because
I was I was basically you know I got
completely sober walked into an empty
room and went out body standing up and
went into a round where I was I felt
like I was headed upwards when I was
suddenly this ginormous beam of light
like an imagined javelin of light and I
was rotating in a wheel of light of
these beams and suddenly I could see
eight other beams of light and a
disembodied voice tells me you're your
soul is inhabiting eight other bodies
and you're only aware of one and and the
voice also says look up because you're
this this wheel of light is only part of
what you're in and before I could look
up my friend who's downstairs basically
he was calling my name and as he was
calling my name I was pulled out of this
space and poured back into my body and
as I was being poured back in I was told
you're not calm you're having the
experience of being car for a thousand
months and and second thing there is no
death and the third thing was tell
everybody and from that you know that
permission almost you know because again
no no drugs involved completely and I
was standing up you know it's completely
wild and I'd never tried DMT and took me
ten years to find it after that and even
then nothing like DMT so completely wild
and you know I found a book or the
knowledge but gnosis book and it was
basically a diagram in this book that
looked exactly like why I'd experienced
and that the figure was called the the
programming station of all so I still
haven't fully understand I understood
but what what then that led me to and
I've never practiced out-of-body
experiences since that was a completely
like a gift
what the super interesting is that when
I had my life review that forty was this
this this ability to leave my body
inside that space and maybe I would
never have even thought of doing that or
felt that I could do that without having
the out-of-body experience previous so
super interesting when we start to use
our transform eights transformative
experiences as material for our own
development and and actually using those
as much as I do because of you know I'm
a computer scientist but I also like to
talk about these experiences because so
much of what you know it's so much of
people you know people don't talk about
them and I think that it's absolutely
vital that we we consider that these
felt experiences as just as important as
anything cognitively we're nearing the
end of the session but perhaps we can
still squeeze in one more question what
do you think Carl yeah go ahead
alright key could you wanna meet
yourself it's okay thank you so much
Carl for the entire presentation I've
made like so many notes and I'm very
thankful to be able to create these
notes in the first place
so my question I'll just read it from
here because I was curious as to why you
put it in the words that you did um
could you clarify your use of the term
dark side and death literacy and I'm
really appreciative of you saying that
Oh like the well what you've said and
the how you said it was the extender of
boundaries into what was previously an
enemy territory
while focusing on like changing and
proving ourselves I realize it's a
little clip a big question but thank you
are you unnamed
you're a mutant
yes sorry um yeah it's actually quite a
part of that was the the death literacy
thing was yeah I think that if we around
the mystery schools and this whole thing
about you
going through a death experience much
like what we are I mean you know I've
definitely been through dark night of
the soul over the last three months and
I think it's so refreshing and vital to
to basically face your mortality I mean
I know friends of mine will believe
they're immortal you know a certain age
you you just do you just don't you don't
get it and so they go and work in
nursing homes in order to get that death
literacy and to you know to try and
counter this this feeling of immortality
and endless time and I think the reason
why the mystery schools and these
initiations are so important is because
you get on with what's really important
in your life you know you don't mess
around anymore you stop acting like and
I do believe we are immortal but not in
these bodies so I think that get on with
your mission whatever it is if your
mission is just a play then get on with
that but the point is is is yeah having
having an awareness and the bit about
the dark side and all that that wasn't
me that was Grant Morrison yeah where
he's talking about basically becoming
you know treat your friends close and
your enemies closer
so you know it's all material where you
know we're in this non duality but we're
also in a in a multiverse of infinite
consciousness and it for me it's all
about consciousness literacy so thank
you for the question all right Wow well
that was I was a fantastic session I
mean everybody's like and all I think of
all this all the amazing things you
should so maybe you could share where we
can find more of your stuff online yeah
sure um just put some put my email in my
email me anything so I can send you the
paper and links to talks and breaking
convention I've got like three talks
every over the last year's um and yeah
I'd love to to keep in touch with the
stoah big fans of you guys doing a
fantastic job Peter with amazing guests
and yeah I'd love to do this again
alright well thank you so much for
coming on the stoah and I don't know if
Peter wanna you want to say something
yeah there's two final thoughts Carl
thanks so much we'd love to I consider
you part of the the stone village now so
you're part of the family feel free to
come back anytime if you have any ideas
you'd like to chat or I think Tyson said
she'd come back for some kind of reality
hacking psycho tech love to see that if
there if you can conjure up something
there
Nick think for it thank you for I'm
seeing again today and maybe are you
still there
I do want to maybe chat about the
session we're having in an hour
um yeah in an hour we're going to have a
session Jeremy I'm gonna look up his
name sorry I did not expect to be doing
shut up give me one second we're all
practicing our stoicism here at the
store
Jeremy Johnson Jeremy Johnson is gonna
be talking about liminality and how
that's sort of like the essential
underlying emotional currents to the
whole meta crisis that we're dealing
with now he's a you know gonna be
grounded into my integral philosophy and
stuff like that he's a really really
chill cool guy he is just fun to sit and
be in the presence of so that's going on
at noon Eastern Time if you guys want to
drop by I think that you'll really enjoy
his company
yeah and he just thank you maybe he just
launched a new platform called limo news
which is pretty cool I recommend
checking it out and then Eric Davis who
Carl mentioned he's coming in next week
the high weirdness of kovat that's at
June 10th at 4 p.m. Eastern Time
so check that out as well alright
everyone thanks so much see you soon